<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Because that in the following discourse the reason is recited and answered, why my ministry is rejected and not received by this ignorant, but more especially corrupt world; therefore I thought it expedient and necessary to publish the same.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5107G</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184555</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077645</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077645</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2274:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Because that in the following discourse the reason is recited and answered, why my ministry is rejected and not received by this ignorant, but more especially corrupt world; therefore I thought it expedient and necessary to publish the same.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: So witnesseth Richard Stafford ...</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Sion College Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Political activity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151750:1"/>
            <argument>
               <p>Becauſe that in the following Diſcourſe the Reaſon is Recited and Anſwered, why my Miniſtry is Rejected and not Received by this Ignorant, but more eſpecially Corrupt World; therefore I thought it Expedient and Neceſſary to Publiſh the ſame.</p>
            </argument>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>EZEKIEL ii. v.</bibl>
                  <p>And they, whether they will hear, or whether they will for bear (for they are a Rebellious Houſe) yet ſhall know that there hath been a Prophet among them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF we could now know and diſcern, as we ſhall know and diſcern <hi>(In the latter Daies ye ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it perfectly)</hi> when we ſhall be actually car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried forth from Time to Eternity, then we ſhould have other kind of Thoughts concerning the Things of God, then we have in this Life, and on this Earth. <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into Heaven?</hi> That is, <hi>to bring Chriſt down from above, Or who ſhall deſcend into the Deep?</hi> That is, <hi>to bring up Chriſt again from the Dead: But what ſaith it? The Word is nigh thee, even in thy Mouth and in thy Heart,</hi> that is, <hi>the Word of Faith which we Preach.</hi> The Word of Faith will in a manner do all this, that is, bring down things out of Heaven that they are made known unto us, all one as the things of this Earth. This <hi>Word of Faith,</hi> makes inviſible things to be in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner viſible, and things Future to be Preſent unto us. Of this ſort are the whole Scriptures of God, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an <hi>Orderly Declaration of things which are moſt ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed among us.</hi> So that they are the <hi>Word of Faith</hi> which we Preach. The Scripture doth chiefly ſpeak of things which are yet to come, and will be fulfilled after that we are gone off from the Stage of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151750:2"/> this Earth, and we ſhall find it ſo upon the reflection and remembrance.</p>
            <p>Of this ſort is the Text I have here choſen, which partly ſpeaks of things Preſent, and partly of things to come. <hi>And they, whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear.</hi> Hereby their Proof and Trial is had as to this preſent Time: for this denotes forth their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent kind of Demeanour and Behaviour hereupon. But by that Phraſe, <hi>Yet ſhall know,</hi> The particle <hi>ſhall,</hi> is an Adverb of Futurity; and by what is further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed on, <hi>That there hath been a Prophet among them,</hi> is ſhewn forth a Recollection, that ſo it hath been, which they were not aware off, and did not altogether ſo clearly diſcern then.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon of my chooſing this Text to Diſcourſe on here, is to this effect, Inaſmuch as I have been a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher unto the People of this my Generation and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſeveral Years laſt paſt, and as yet my Miniſtry hath been Rejected and not Received amongſt them; whereupon I am forced to make this, or the like return, That <hi>I have ſpread out my hands all the day unto a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people, Iſa. 65. 2. I have laboured in vain, and ſpent my ſtrength for nought, and in vain; yet ſurely my work is with the Lord, and my judgment with my God,</hi> Iſa. 49. 4. As for every Sin there is ſome ſeeming excuſe, ſo for their not hearing the Word of the Lord at my Mouth, There hath been ſuch an imagination in the Minds of People. To ſpeak out thoſe <hi>Thoughts of Heart,</hi> it ſeems to be to this purpoſe, <hi>As ſome did contend with Peter that he went in to Men Uncircumciſed and did eat with them,</hi> Acts 11. 3. So the people of this Nation have heard a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain kind of Rumour or Report, That I have Written and Spoken ſundry things in behalf of a Papiſt; and inaſmuch as Popery is not <hi>the truth as it is in Jeſus</hi> (as indeed it is not, which I do hereby acknowledge as much as themſelves) From hence they would Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly and Falſly Reaſon and Conclude, That I have not Taught, nor yet as long as I retain theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, do <hi>I teach the way of God in truth.</hi> And therefore it is that they <hi>turn their backs,</hi> and they refuſe to hear the Word of the Lord Preached by me.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151750:2"/>
            <p>If in all this, I have not been unfaithfull to God, nor yet in handling his Word, <hi>Neither have we dealt falſly in thy Covenant; Our heart is not turned back, neither have our ſteps declined from thy way,</hi> Pſal. 44. 17. 18. But I have affirmed his Word and Commandment only in the ſame manner as they ſtand Recorded in the <hi>Book of the Lord:</hi> Then thoſe non Hearers are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced out of the Law as Tranſgreſſors; for refuſal or neglect to hear the Word of God, is Sin and Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It ſeems very ſtrange, That thoſe who ſeem to Preach and Talk very much againſt Sin; yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this matter, give way unto, and are guilty thereof. But it is no new or unuſual thing, that ſome ſpeak againſt Sin in the general, and yet at the very ſame time, themſelves are guilty of the ſame in the particular Nature hereof.</p>
            <p>True it is, that Popery is made up of Idolatry, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Errour. But yet we are in no wiſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Chriſtian Religion, which doth command, That <hi>ye reſiſt not evil,</hi> Mat. 5. 39. <hi>Recompence to no Man</hi> (and if ſo, it ought not to be done to a Papiſt) <hi>Evil for Evil. Be not overcome of Evil, but overcome Evil with good,</hi> Rom. 12. 17, 21. So that it is not true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt Religion, but contrary to it, To Murder, Rob, or do any Evil or Wrong unto a Papiſt. Unleſs Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are become altogether ignorant and dull of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, It is a moſt eaſie thing to be conceived and underſtood, That a Man may be no Papiſt, and yet do no Evil or Wrong unto a Papiſt. Agreeable hereunto is the Will and Commandment of the moſt High God, who doth not eſteem Papiſts to be worſe than Idolaters, Strangers, Heathen or Publicans of Old. As to them, God declares himſelf and his Will to be on this manner, <hi>I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a ſwift witneſs againſt falſe Swearers, and againſt thoſe that turn aſide the Stranger from his right,</hi> Mal. 3. 5. Such is the Revealed Will of God. And moreover, it is the ſame Robbery and Injuſtice in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151750:3"/> Nature of things, to diſpoſeſs or ſpoil a Papiſt, as any other Perſon.</p>
            <p>What I have Written in behalf of a Papiſt, did amount to no more then this, That meerly or ſo far only as he was a Papiſt, he ought not to have been turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſide from his Right; which I grounded from <hi>Mal.</hi> 3, 5. aforecited: And alſo from <hi>Lam. 3. 35, 36. To turn aſide the Right of a Man before the Face of the Moſt High, To ſubvert a Man in his cauſe, the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth not.</hi> Which is as plain a Declaration of the Mind and Will of God, as any thing in the World can be; and altogether as plain and ſelf-evident as that maxim is, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do unto ye, do ye even ſo to them, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> In this place of the Lamentations it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaid, <hi>Man,</hi> indefinitely, it extends equally and all one, to Sinner as to Saint, to <hi>Gentile</hi> as well as to the <hi>Jew,</hi> to Bond or Free, yea to all of the Race and Line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of Mankind, <hi>To turn aſide the Right of any Man whatſoever, or to ſubvert any Man whatſoever in his cauſe the Lord approveth not.</hi> So that, if herein I have only delivered and made known the truth as it is in the Scriptures of God, then alſo it is the truth as it is in Jeſus, for Jeſus is the Word of God: Then I ſay, That <hi>when the Dead ſmall and great ſhall ſtand before God,</hi> I ſhall have <hi>boldneſs</hi> in that Day, when I ſhall at the Bar of his Judgment Seat, implead the People of this my Generation and Nation, for their not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or not receiving that part of the Word of God which was committed to my Miniſtration; and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may meet with fear, ſhame and confuſion of Face, when they are called to give an Account for the ſame; then alſo ſhall they know who did <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, That there hath been a Prophet among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are in our Text called <hi>Rebellious</hi> who did <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear;</hi> for ſo many things in the Scriptures of God are ſpoken forth againſt them who are non hearers or who refuſe to hear his Word. <hi>Seeing thou hateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and caſteſt my words behind thee,</hi> Pſal. 50. 17. <hi>This evil people which refuſe to hear my words,</hi> Jer. 13. 10.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151750:3"/> Yea, there is much more ſaid againſt them then thoſe Cautions are againſt <hi>Deceivers,</hi> or <hi>Take heed what ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear.</hi> Where again it is obſervable, That we are not forbid to hear but intimation is rather given, That we ſhould hear, as well as <hi>prove all things;</hi> for how could we <hi>Prove</hi> them, unleſs we did firſt hear and know them. We ought to <hi>Take heed what we hear,</hi> that is, Examine and Prove well what we do hear. Seeing that theſe things are ſo, I admire, how any who pretend to have the real fear of God, can or do turn their backs upon the Preaching of his Word.</p>
            <p>Such who <hi>forbear</hi> and refuſe to Hear, Read, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, would have the Word of God (which like its Author, is without <hi>Uariableneſs or Shadow of turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing)</hi> to be faſhioned and modelled according to their own Imaginations and Luſts. Which ſame Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and Luſts of Men are different from, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto the Word of God. A manifeſt Evidence that there is a ſpreading and prevailing Corruption, Tranſgreſſion and Iniquity in this Nation; becauſe that the multitude of People is ſo very much zealous for it; for the multitude have been all along, for what is either contrary unto, or different from the Law and Revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Will of God. <hi>Even from the days of your Fathers ye are gone away from mine Ordinances, and have not kept them,</hi> Mal. 3. 7. This Word <hi>Ordinance,</hi> doth denote an eſtabliſhed and fixed Order of things according as God hath appointed them. And here it is witneſſed and affirmed, That in the ſeveral Generations and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, the People have varied from, and have <hi>not kept them.</hi> Now there is more credit to be given unto the affirmation of the Word of God (that being a forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his future Judgment) then to all the Uindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Hypocritical Pretences of the People themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, that they have not gone away from his Ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, when indeed they have; or then indeed is to be had to all the ſayings, of Biſhops, Doctors, or Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, the Prieſts and People themſelves, <hi>Who Rob Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Mother, and ſay it is no Tranſgreſſion;</hi> Prov. 28.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151750:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151750:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151750:5"/> 24. When indeed it is a Tranſgreſſion. And ſo it will clearly appear at the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, when another Scene and Face of things will be ſeen over what is now; then they <hi>which juſtifie themſelves before Men, and who are highly eſteemed amongſt Men will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination in the ſight of God,</hi> Luke 16. 15. And on the other hand, that ſolid, ſincere, unaffected Piety, that univerſal Zeal for God, and for all his Commandments indefinitely without exception, not keeping ſome and neglecting others, as the manner of many is at this Day, but an actual obſervance of all them, not <hi>breaking the leaſt Commandment,</hi> Mat. 5. 19. For any ſpecious end or pretence whatever, although this be now ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and reproached by Men, who are the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, will yet be commended and accepted by God.</p>
            <p>In all probability and likelihood, the Stream and Multitude of the Jewiſh People, did run againſt <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> with as much Zeal, Heat, and Enmity: As we have ſeen and known the greater part of the Inhabitants thereof, do <hi>hate</hi> him that was King over this Nation, and for theſe twelve Years laſt paſt, <hi>They would not have him Reign over them,</hi> Luke 19. 14. And that for the ſame Reaſon: For as our People feared that ſuch a one would Conquer and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave them after <hi>French</hi> Methods, and compel them to Popery. So peradventure the Antient <hi>Jews</hi> might have ſecret indignation and hatred againſt <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> becauſe he had made a Conqueſt over them; for this belongs to Conquerors, to be inwardly and ſecretly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though they are outwardly feared. And alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was an Heathen, an Idolater and a Stranger; and as it was <hi>Not lawful for a Man that was a Jew to keep company with any other Nation,</hi> ſo they did conceive, and keep up unkindneſs and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt them. Notwithſtanding this mind of the Jewiſh Nation; yet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> a true Prophet of the Lord in his ſeventeenth Chapter, doth ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>undry thing, in behalf of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> according to humane Apprehenſion; whereas in Truth he ſpeaks, for the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151750:5"/> 
               <hi>Oath and Covenant of God,</hi> which the Jewiſh Nation had taken unto him. So that here it might have been Objected and Upbraided unto <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> What <hi>doſt thou go about to deſtroy the Worſhip of God, which at that day was among the Jews, and to bring in the Heatheniſh cuſtoms?</hi> Inaſmuch as thou would'ſt have us retain our ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto an Heathen King, and <hi>not rebell againſt him,</hi> as we have done: Nevertheleſs the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> doth there ſpeak ſundry things againſt their Rebellion: Nay, It is not ſo much <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> as the Spirit of God God which ſpake by him, who knows beſt what is his own Laws, and what is pleaſing in his Sight. <hi>Seek ye out of the Book of the Lord, and read;</hi> for therein it is written, <hi>That we ſhould have our Converſation honeſt among the Gentiles, leaſt the Name of the Lord ſhould be Blaſphemed, and the way of Truth evil ſpoken of amongſt them: That we ſhould carry out ſelves wiſely towards them that are without. Recompence to no Man evil for evil, Provide things honeſt in the ſight of all Men: Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.</hi> Now ſeeing that our God hath given ſuch and ſuch Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and many more to the ſame purpoſe, as may be ſeen in the Old and New Teſtament; here to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude unto that ſaying of <hi>Peter,</hi> in <hi>Acts 11. 17. What are we</hi> the Miniſters and Preachers of his Word, <hi>that we ſhould withſtand God?</hi> Or that we ſhould vary from his Word and Commandment? Or that we ſhould be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſo as not to make mention of this Word and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of the Lord, becauſe that it will diſpleaſe the People, in that they have lately acted contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Far be it from me, and <hi>let my Tongue cleave to the Roof of my Mouth,</hi> if ever I ſhould be a Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſer after this manner. <hi>For if I yet pleaſed Men, I ſhould not be the ſervant of Chriſt.</hi> By his Grace and Aſſiſtance, and inviſible Protection, I will go on, and proceed to behave my ſelf <hi>truly in his Covenant,</hi> that is, to ſpeak out and aſſert the Commandments of God, exactly in the very ſame manner as they are: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever my Miniſtry is Received or Rejected by the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; or whether I do bear the Scorn and Reproofs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151750:6"/> of the High and Mighty People, as <hi>David</hi> himſelf wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth he did, whoſe example herein I am confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med unto. I am determined through Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth me, to <hi>follow the Lamb,</hi> who is the Word, and the Word is God, and ſo the conducts and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Divine Truth, <hi>Whether ſoever it goes,</hi> whether I have many or few hearers; for herein God will be more glorified; and hereby I ſhall give a good and right Account of my Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>It hath been the way and method of Satan, in the ſeveral Generations and Countries; and ſo he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues to do at this Day, that where he ſees and diſcerns (for he is both a knowing and diſcerning Spirit) that ſuch a ones Miniſtry would do more good; than others; or that <hi>God hath anointed</hi> ſuch a particular Creature of his <hi>with the Oyl of gladneſs above his fellows;</hi> There Satan the Enemy will labour and endeavour ſome way or other to puzzle and perplex his Miniſtry, ſo as to render it either of none, or if that is not poſſible, yet of leſs effect. And though what is of God, will ſtand in ſpite of Men or Devils; and the ſame will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived nevertheleſs, by ſome of the Servants of God: Yet many others in ſuch a time of Temptation and Trial, will fall and go utterly away. For Example whereof, we may have recourſe unto the Hiſtory of the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles; whoſe Writings and ſayings do abundantly ſhew forth and manifeſt the Reproaches and perverſe Uſage of the People con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them. Of our Lord and Saviour himſelf, <hi>Being made better then the Angels;</hi> Heb. 1. 4. And greater then all the Prophets, yet we thus read, <hi>He is deſpiſed and rejected of Men; he is deſpiſed and we eſteemed him not,</hi> Iſa. 53. 3. And yet in him was the words of our Text literally fulfilled. <hi>And they, whether they will hear, or whether they will forbear (for they are a rebellious Houſe) yet ſhall know that there hath been a Prophet among them.</hi> Even that Prophet of whom God by <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpoke, <hi>I will raiſe them up a Prophet from among their Brethren like unto thee, and will put my words in his mouth, and he ſhall ſpeak unto them all that I ſhall command him.</hi> Yet
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151750:6"/> in the Days of his Fleſh, ſome of the People of that Generation did hear Chriſt, and others again did <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear</hi> and not hear him. Who Reproached him for a <hi>Deceiver,</hi> Mat. 27. 63. <hi>And many of them ſaid, he hath a Devil, and is mad, Why hear ye him?</hi> Joh. 10. 20. And yet ſome of the very ſame Perſons, after they had Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified and Put him to Death, then they did confeſs and acknowledge, <hi>Now the Centurion and thoſe that were with him</hi> (even thoſe People who had Reproached, Perſecuted and Rejected him) <hi>watching Jeſus, ſaw the Earthquake, and thoſe things that were done they fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed greatly; ſaying, truly this was the Son of God.</hi> After that they had crucified the Lord Jeſus, then they did know, and own him to have been a <hi>Prophet;</hi> yea the very Son of God. And ſo it was with the other Prophets, after they had Perſecuted and Slain them; and after they had <hi>finiſhed their Teſtimony and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> or after that they were Dead; then the People could Remember and look back, that ſuch an one was a Prophet or an eminent Servant of the Lord. <hi>Lo, when this is come to paſs, then ſhall it be known that there hath been a Prophet among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fooliſh and abſurd Nature of Men, doth more prize and eſteem of things by their want, then by the having them. Like as we value Health in the time of Sickneſs: So ſuch a precious Jewel as a ſound, faithful underſtanding Miniſtry, which is Health and Life to our Souls, which feeds them with Knowledge and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; even this is more eſteemed when it is loſt then when had and enjoyed. Like as in the time of <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, The Word of the Lord was precious, in thoſe Days there was no open viſion.</hi> So when a thing is common, or preſent, or eaſily had, then alſo it is apt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and not eſteemed off: But when the ſame is paſt by and irrecoverable, then they wiſh for and deſire it.</p>
            <p>Another Reaſon why thoſe eminent Inſtruments of the Glory of God, in their ſeveral Generations, were rejected by the People thereof; becauſe they did Preach and Teach what did vehemently and violently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151750:7"/> the Luſts and Will of Men, and they would not endure that, but keep unto their own Luſts ſtill; and thereupon they Reproached, Rejected and evil en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated the <hi>Servants of the most High God, who did teach the way of Salvation.</hi> There is ſomewhat of this in all, even the worſt and moſt diſobedient of Men: They have ſome Senſe and Apprehenſion of the Great God over all, and they fain would be at Peace and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with him; for as he doth good, ſo he can puniſh and make miſerable, as is evident to the moſt Ungodly and Ignorant, by that Sickneſs and Death which he ſends upon the Children of Men; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though they have Tranſgreſſed, and do ſtill go aſide from the way of his Commandments: They would ſo have it, as if God had given no ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments at all. Like the queſtion of the Serpent (by whoſe Temptation they are ſtill acted) <hi>Yea, hath God ſaid, ye ſhall not eat of every Tree in the Garden?</hi> By which he would cunningly ſuggeſt and inſtil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Minds, as if God had not ſaid ſo. Even ſo a Thought doth ariſe in the Hearts of the Diſobedient, as if God had given no ſuch Commandments. But when his faithful Miniſters do affirm that he hath, then they ſeem to be <hi>Setters forth of ſtrange Doctrins,</hi> and to <hi>Bring ſome new things to their ears.</hi> Hence there are that <hi>Raiſe up ſtrife and contention,</hi> Hab. 1. 3. For theſe <hi>Ungodly Men walking after their own Luſts</hi> will ſtrive and contend againſt ſuch who Preach the Word and Commandment of God, againſt their Ungodlineſs and Luſts. Therefore as it is in the following words, <hi>The Law is ſlacked,</hi> ver. 4. When it is either forgotten or broken by them.</p>
            <p>If we look back unto the particular Hiſtory of the Prophets and Apoſtles, we ſhall find that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches and evil Entreaty of the People againſt them did ariſe for this very cauſe. What a ſtir was there againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> made by <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his fellow Crafts Men, when he Preached againſt the Idolatry of the People of <hi>Athens;</hi> and ſo he mentions that he was evil intreated at <hi>Philippi</hi> for the Like Reaſon. The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151750:7"/> Inhabitants of both Places did imagine that they did Pleaſe, Atone and Worſhip the Great God of the World, by thoſe their Idolatrous and Superſtitious Rites and Cuſtoms: But when the Apoſtle did from the Spirit of the moſt High God, contradict them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then the <hi>Heathen were in a rage,</hi> by having heard that heretofore themſelves followed <hi>a vain thing.</hi> The Doctrine of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> as to this matter, is exactly fitted and applyed againſt theſe their falſe Imaginations. <hi>God that made the World, and all things therein, ſeeing that he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, neither is Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with Mens hands as though he needed any thing, ſeeing that he giveth to all Life and Breath and all things. Foraſmuch then as we are the offspring of God, we ought not to think that the God-head is like unto Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or Stone graven by art and Mans device.</hi> Now Preaching and Publiſhing hath that Effect, that ſome do believe, receive and obey the things Spoken or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, others do kick againſt them; as it is ſaid in the ſame Chapter, that they mocked at the following Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of this ſame Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>It is a work of an hard Nature to ſtrive againſt the Luſts, long received cuſtoms, eſtabliſhed Rites and Habits of Men: For cuſtom is a ſecond Nature, and when People have been long uſed to a thing, you had almoſt as good tear or pluck away one of their Limbs, as go about to remove or perſwade People off from it. <hi>Can a Leopard change his Spots, or an Aethopian his Skin? So may they do well, who have been accuſtomed to do evil.</hi> That is, it is very hard and difficult. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs if that ſame cuſtom be evil or vain; then as the ſame God did Create the outward Man; ſo in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or New Creation of him, which is called the New Birth, or Regeneration (which ſignifies a being born again) the Grace of God will perſwade off from, and get rid of that ſame evil or vain Cuſtom. Saith the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>If after the manner of Men I have fought with Beaſts at Epheſus.</hi> Now Beaſts will (what lieth in them, unleſs they be broken off from it)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151750:8"/> unto their Luſts, and to their Cuſtoms; and ſo long as Men are of the ſame Mind, they are after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Beaſts: Like as a Carriers Horſe will go on in its wonted way; ſo <hi>The brutiſh among the People</hi> are for doing ſtill (though it be evil or falſe) what they have been uſed and accuſtomed unto; for ſuch are led by Sence and Memory, and not by Reaſon or Judgment. Now Faith is an higher and more ſublime Principle of Action, which carries above all theſe: And where the Man doth live by Faith, and act by Faith, then <hi>He puts away childiſh things,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. 11. Then he puts away the inferiour Principles; by which others, and perhaps himſelf formerly did Act and Live. And now he is acted by Faith only. Whereby he becomes ſomewhat above and beyond a Man, as Reaſon Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances above a Beaſt; <hi>For Fleſh and Blood doth not reveal theſe things unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The juſt ſhall live by his Faith,</hi> Hab. 2. 4. Which is a great and obſervable Scripture, in that it is thrice quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> and it is written for our Inſtruction and <hi>Admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi> To lead and bring People over unto this Noble and Divine State of Living by Faith, is the end of all our Writing Books and Preaching Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. But the generality of Mankind hath been ſo long <hi>Settled upon the lees,</hi> and ſunk down into Earthlineſs, Senſe and the things of this Life, that they are not ſo eaſily and ſoon raiſed up to this Spiritual frame of Mind, which if obtained, would influence all their Actions. There is that in the Hearts of Natural Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate People, and alſo that remainder of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and of the old Nature, even in the Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; that theſe laſt do grow weary of, and the others do ſtrive againſt the Heavenly ſeed of true Doctrine. There is a reluctancy in the former, and an aukward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the latter. And as it is written, <hi>There was War in Heaven, Michal with his Angels fought with the Dragon and his Angels.</hi> So hence doth ariſe War in the Soul of Man: Chriſt Jeſus, with the words he puts into the Heart, doth fight with the Devil and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151750:8"/> his Suggeſtions, and alſo with what Temptations ariſe from the Fleſh, and from the things of this World; and accordingly as one prevails or the other, ſo is the Man determined to Good or Evil, Truth or Falſhood, Right or Wrong.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a way which ſeemeth right in a Mans own eyes, but the paths thereof lead unto Death.</hi> And as God hath made our Nature with a ſtrong bent and tendency to the thing that right is; ſo even in our backſlidings and goings aſide, we do not commonly any thing that is wrong, but under a ſhew and outward appearance of right. <hi>The time cometh, that whoſoever killeth you, will t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ink that he doth God ſervice,</hi> John 16. 2. Said Jeſus to his Diſciples, and that was committing a grievous Sin, even Murther it ſelf. Yet however ſtrange it may ſeem, yet ſo it is, that People are ſo infatuated and deluded as to think that they did ſerve and obey God, whilſt they were acting a thing contrary to his Laws. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms what was afore obſerved, That People think that they do keep the Commandments of God, even whilſt they break and tranſgreſs them, and they fain would have it ſo as if they had not ſinned. An Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample hereof may be ſeen in the Hiſtory of the fall of <hi>Adam. Now the Serpent was made more ſubtil then any beaſt of the field, which the Lord God had made: And he ſaid unto the Woman; yea hath God ſaid, ye ſhall not eat of every tree of the Garden,</hi> Gen. 3. 1. By which he would cunningly inſinuate in the firſt place, as if God had given no ſuch Commandment; which yet was ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident to their Hearts and Conſciences, That the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent himſelf could not well gain-ſay and deny it, as appears by the Anſwer of the Woman, in ver. 2. 3. Whereupon the Serpent did reply in ver. 4. 5. And frame another kind of Temptation; unto which the Man and Woman do unhappily yeild. But then it being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>And the eyes of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked.</hi> By their Eyes being opened, may be at firſt ſuppoſed, as if their Condition was not hereupon become worſe but better for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: For ſo it ſeems, where thoſe who heretofore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151750:9"/> were blind or Blear-eyed do ſee, Here again it may be perceived, from the following Verſe: There was alſo in them, a ſecret conſciouſneſs that they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God; for it was this which made them hide <hi>Themſelves from the preſence of the Lord God, among the trees of the Garden.</hi> From all which conſidered together, this true Obſervation may be gathered, That though Satan would ſuggeſt unto Sinners and Tranſgreſſors; as if God had given no Commandment againſt what he tempts unto; yet nevertheleſs, after they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſame, there is a conſciouſneſs, and full conviction within them, that they have alſo herein done ſomewhat to offend and diſpleaſe God; which is alſo ſenſible unto themſelves, by that guilt which doth appear forth upon their inward parts, and by that fear which they labour under.</p>
            <p>In every inſtance of Tranſgreſſion before the fact is committed, <hi>A deceived Heart doth turn them aſide:</hi> And ſo it is afterwards, <hi>The deceived Heart</hi> doth continue and hinder them from coming to Repentance. Sin doth caſt a Cloud over the underſtanding, which doth hinder the influence of the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and deprives of the knowledge of things Divine. Remarkable is that of <hi>Daniel 12. 10. Many ſhall be purified and made white and tried; but the wicked ſhall do wickedly, and none of the wicked ſhall underſtand; but the wiſe ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</hi> Hence it is, <hi>even to them which ſtumble at the word, being diſobedient,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 8. That People are ſo puzzled and perplexed at the works and doings of God. <hi>We have ſinned with our Fathers, we have committed iniquity, and done wickedly,</hi> Pſal. 106. 6. And what is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent of that, may be ſeen in the next verſe. <hi>Our Fathers underſtood not thy wonders in Aegypt.</hi> Therefore it was becauſe they had ſinned and done wickedly, and committed iniquity. This is the very Reaſon why People do underſtand ſo very little according to truth of the Works and Doings of God; for God will not manifeſt himſelf unto the Soul which is defiled with Sin, Iniquity or Filthineſs. And ſo if People were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Obedient to the Word of our Miniſtry, and if they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151750:9"/> would come to hear it (for their refuſal do that is one Act of their Diſobedience) then they would be ſatisfied and convinced of our Truth, Sincerity and rightneſs therein: Even that we do <hi>Not handle the Word of God deceitfully, but by manifeſtation of the truth, commending our ſelves to every Mans Conſcience in the ſight of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 4. 2. And that we do ſpeak out the Truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth, not making leſs of it, nor concealing any part of it; as the manner of moſt Preachers and Teachers is, leaſt they diſpleaſe their hearers. <hi>If any Man will do his Will, he ſhall know of the Doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I ſpeak of my ſelf,</hi> John 7. 17. So on the other hand from what is written, <hi>That we might turn from our iniquities, and underſtand thy truth,</hi> Dan. 9. 13. We may learn and gather, that the only way to come to the knowledge of the things of God, is by Obedience and keeping his Commandments: As contrariwiſe it is only becauſe of their Sin, Iniquity and Tranſgreſſions, that any do remain in ignorance and darkneſs.</p>
            <p>As <hi>David</hi> ſaith by the Spirit, <hi>Come and hear all ye that fear God, and I will declare what he hath done for my Soul,</hi> Pſal. 66. 16. So we (both Miniſters and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) are allowed, yea in Duty we ought to declare and make known our ſeveral Experiences between God and our Souls; that if the ſame be good, they may be for the edifying and inſtructing one another; or if they be evil and failings, then it is for the warning of each other, that we may all ſee the Rock, whereon our Souls, or the Souls of others, had almoſt been Shipwracked; or the place and ſtumbling Block, whereat our ſteps had well nigh ſlipped: Or if any of the Miniſters of God lie under Reproaches and falſe Cenſures (as my preſent Caſe is) then we may <hi>Rehearſe the matter from the beginning and expound it by order unto the people,</hi> Acts 11. 4. We have Examples hereof in the Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul;</hi> whoſe ſecond Epiſtle to the Corinthians, is chiefly made up of Apologies and Vindications of himſelf, from falſe Calumnies and Reports. We may find the like in the other Prophets, Miniſters and Servants of God.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151750:10"/> 
               <hi>And the Rebuke of his people he ſhall take away from off all the Earth,</hi> Iſa. 25. 8. So in the mean while he is well pleaſed, that according to the Knowledge, Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Truth he hath given them, they ſhould do it themſelves.</p>
            <p>In miſunderſtandings between Miniſter and People, and ſo between Man and Man, there is moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome fault on both ſides; So it is here, beſides the Sin and Ignorance, Perverſeneſs, Stubbornneſs, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Diſobedience to Gods Word and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is in the People of this Generation and Nation: I cannot ſay neither, <hi>That I have made my Heart clean;</hi> or that I am wholly without fault or blame. Though here to enter in my Proteſtation, <hi>In all that hath come upon us, I have not forgotten God, nor behaved my ſelf falſly in his Covenant.</hi> When I taught and affirmed conſtantly, that it was his Commandment and revealed Will, <hi>I will be a ſwift witneſs againſt falſe ſwearers and againſt them that turn aſide the ſtranger from his right,</hi> Mal. 3. 5. Yet in the bearing forth and ſuffering for that Teſtimony, I gave way to ſo many things, which did ſavour of Men, and of the fleſhly corrupt Nature that was in me, that the work was ſpoiled and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>managed by me: That even ſeveral of his Saints and Servants were ready to imagine and conclude, that there was nothing at all of God in it. <hi>When I was num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among the tranſgreſſors,</hi> Iſa. 53. 12. Bleſſed be God for conforming me therein to the example of Jeſus Chriſt uor Lord; and I was put into Priſon, yea into the ſame place with real Criminals, who were <hi>there juſtly, for they received the due reward of their deeds,</hi> Luke 23. 40, 41. But I had <hi>done nothing amiſs</hi> as to that matter; yet I was fooliſhly, falſly, and ignorantly dealt withal and proceeded againſt, as a breaker of Mans Laws; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth only becauſe I did exhort them to keep and to do according to the Laws of God; and yet ſtill <hi>Let it be done according to the Law, Ezra.</hi> 10. 3. And I had admoniſhed them of the breach and violation thereof, in order to bring them again unto his Law and into the way of his Commandments. I did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151750:10"/> more, or beyond, or beſides this. But for me to be uſed as a Tranſgreſſour for this doing, by them who in truth were the Tranſgreſſours themſelves, this was ſtrange Sottiſhneſs and Ignorance in my Perſecutors and Oppreſſours, <hi>who did ſeek after my Soul, they have not ſet God before them, Selah.</hi> Pſal. 54. 3.</p>
            <p>Whilſt I was in Priſon I thought That God ſhould do ſomewhat more for my Deliverance (yea, ſometimes a vain Imagination did ariſe, That it ſhould be in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner extraordinary by way of Miracle) then he did for my fellow Priſoners. For I thought it hard; yea, an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Suggeſtion did peep forth, and was juſt perceived in my Mind, as if it would be Unrighteouſneſs in God if he ſhould ſuffer me to be plagued and holden like other Men; But bleſſed be his Name, it was not ſo with me; For he hath been with me in five Troubles, and hath <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from ſo great a Death, and doth deliver: In whom we truſt that he will yet deliver us,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 10. And he cauſed the <hi>Enemy to intreat me well in the time of Evil:</hi> For in every Priſon or Houſe of Confinement I was in, I had more favour and kindneſs ſhewed unto me, then any other Priſoner. But as to the former part of this Thought of mine, a ſeaſonable Anſwer did recur to my Mind, on this wiſe, <hi>viz,</hi> If thou wouldſt have God do more for thee then for other People in ſeeming like outward Condition, then thou ſhouldeſt ſee well to it, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour that Thou, even thou, doſt exceed and go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond thoſe my fellow Creatures and Brethren in Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Holineſs, and by a greater Zeal for the Name and Glory of God; and by a greater Diligence and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to Promote and Propagate his Religion and Truth in the World; Through and by thy Sufferings, <hi>To bring many Sons and Daughters unto Glory.</hi> And if God ſhould reſtore unto thee the joy of his Salvation, and uphold thee with his free Spirit, then to make the right infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Practice afterwards, <hi>Then will I teach Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors thy ways, and ſinners ſhall be converted unto thee,</hi> Pſ. 51. 12, 13. For I ſhould be alike Zealous and Earneſt for all the other Commandments, as for thoſe particularly for which I Suffered; And ſo I ſhould have reproved all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151750:11"/> manner of Sin and Tranſgreſſion, even in all People, <hi>From the greateſt to the leaſt:</hi> And ſo in the meaneſt all one as in the higheſt; as I did reprove the Sin and Tranſgreſſion of the Rich and Mighty People; for which my doing, they threw me into Bonds and laid Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on my Loins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holineſs unto the Lord,</hi> and Obedience to all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, is what God indiſpenſably expects and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires from all his Servants and Creatures. But he looks for higher Degrees and a greater Meaſure thereof in his Prophets, unto whom he <hi>Reveals his Secret,</hi> and brings them <hi>near to himſelf.</hi> For ſo it ſhould be done by <hi>the Man whom thou chooſeſt, and cauſeſt to approach unto thee,</hi> Pſal. 65. 4. and whom Almighty God doth delight to Honour. The Pſalmiſt Pronounces ſuch an one <hi>Bleſſed.</hi> For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the more Godly, or the more Devoted and given up to God, any one is, he will have the more Peace and Comfort in this Life, and be the more Happy and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed throughout all Eternity. In the viſible Church of God in the ſeveral Generations and Countries, There have been all along Obſerved to have been thoſe of the <hi>Devouter ſort;</hi> and ſo there was amongſt the Philoſophers or Profeſſors of Philoſophy, a ſtricter ſort then the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the reſt. And truly it is this Devouter ſort and <hi>Stricter ſect of Religion</hi> (I mention this to all that ſhall Hear or Read theſe Words, to quicken and exhort them unto the utmoſt Preciſeneſs <hi>and Circumſpect walking)</hi> who when <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force,</hi> They do alſo thus take it by force. We Read that when the Lord was to deſcend upon Mount <hi>Sinah;</hi> or when <hi>Moſes</hi> was to deliver any extraordinary Meſſage from God unto the People, or the People were to meet with God; Then the People were to Sanctify, Purify and Prepare themſelves four Days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, and not to come near their Wives. And what theſe did for a ſet Time, his Prophets and eſpecial Servants did throughout the general Courſe of their Life. That is, in the Things pertainign to God, they did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>more than others,</hi> Mat. 5. 47. For they were much more Godly than the common ſtandard and ſize of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as it was then in the World.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:151750:11"/>
            <p>But here <hi>I will ſpeak of mine own Infirmities;</hi> Inſtead of my being more Holy and Sanctified then others; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of my being <hi>harmleſs and undefiled, and ſeparated from ſinners:</hi> And whereas I ſhould have exceeded the reſt of my Brethren in Godlineſs (conſidering what kind of Teſtimony I bore forth, and I ſuffered for) yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe I fell into a Worldly kind and manner of Life, and did retain the vain and fooliſh things of Pride, and the Faſhion of this World; all which was in no wiſe agreeable, but contrary unto the Spirit of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Prophets. Good God! How much did I herein fall off and go aſide from his <hi>High and Heavenly Calling?</hi> This ſhews, and hereby it may be diſcerned and ſeen, how eaſy it is for the <hi>Things which ſavour of Men,</hi> and of the fleſhly corrupt Nature, and of the Pride of Life to creep in and intermingle with the beſt and moſt Divine Works. <hi>Now there was a day, when the Sons of God came to preſent themſelves before the Lord, and Satan came alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them,</hi> Job 1. 6. Even ſo in the moſt Divine Things, ſomewhat of the Devil, the World and the Fleſh, will come in and mingle therewith. The beſt Men have moſt Temptations, and the beſt Works meet with the moſt Oppoſition, which would endeavour to defeat and ſpoil it. And ſo when I was employed in a <hi>Noble matter, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a right work</hi> (to allude unto <hi>Jer.</hi> 2, 11.) I did not then ſo carefully and watchfully ſee to it, as in duty I ought to have done, leaſt I ſhould omit or be guilty of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what which would render it of none, or of leſs effect: But through my neglect and failure herein (I wiſh I could ſpeak it <hi>Weeping)</hi> Satan got an Advantage over me, as to ſerve his own Peſtilent Deſtructive Ends, in Letting, Hindring and Reſiſting of Good.</p>
            <p>I had need to take up a great Lamentation as to my ſelf, even <hi>To Weep with the Weeping of Jazer,</hi> Jer. 48. 32. As I <hi>Remember from whence I am fallen.</hi> And I ſhould herein <hi>Repent and do the firſt works.</hi> As I Recollect and can apprehend how very much I am now fallen ſhort of what I was Originally Created unto. I have often heard a ſecret and ſtill Voice ſpeaking unto my Spirit, like that in the Prophet. <hi>O Iſrael thou art my Servant, in whom I will be glorified.</hi> And ſo it hath ſeemed to me; As if
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151750:12"/> Almighty God had called me by my expreſs outward Name <hi>O RICHARD STAFFORD,</hi> Thou art my Servant and Creature, in whom I will be glorified. Truly this is a great word, and belongs to every Inhabitant throughout the whole Earth, whether Male or Female, Bond or Free, High or Low, Rich or Poor, they are all and ſeverally the Servants or Creatures of God, in whom he will be Glorified. That is, either in their Salvation or Condemnation. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himſelf; yea, even the Wicked for the day of Evil,</hi> Prov. 16. 4. The Servants of God are ſuch who obey him and keep his Commandments, and do the Things which pleaſe him: In theſe he is glorified to their own Good and Comforts. But thoſe again may be more properly ſtiled the Creatures of God than his Servants, who live at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and in forgetfulneſs of their Maker; and in theſe alſo he will be glorified to their own Evil and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that day there ſhall be upon the Bells of the Horſes, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs unto the Lord,</hi> Zech. 14. 20. So it ſhould be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon the Fore head of each of us; and it ſhould be engraven upon the Tables of our Heart; ſo that it may be continually in our Mind and Remembrance. O Man or Woman, calling Him or Her by their reſpective Names, Thou art my Servant, in whom the inviſible God will be glorified. As this following is a nearer and more honourable Relation. <hi>Wherefore come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing; and I will receive you, And will be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto you, and ye ſhall be my Sons and Daughters, ſaith the Lord</hi> Almighty 2 Cor. 6. 17. 18. Even ſo it is here, it is a better and more comfortable Diverſity for the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to ſay unto us, Thou art my Servant in whom I will be glorified; then if he ſhould only ſay, Thou art my Creature in whom I will be glorified. <hi>For his Servants ſhall ſerve him,</hi> Rev. 22. 3. But amidſt the Common and Promiſcuous multitude of Mankind, There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Rebels and Enemies, in whom he will be glorified though it be to their Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And they come unto thee as the people cometh, and they ſit before thee as my people, and they hear thy words, but they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151750:12"/> will not do them; for with their mouth they ſhew much love but their heart goeth after covetouſneſs,</hi> Ezek. 33. 31. And ſo by the outward poſture of People, and by their coming to the publick places of his Worſhip they make a ſhew of much Honour, Reverence and Obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; but their Heart goeth after their own Pleaſure or Profit. They are ſtill for doing their own Will, and for going after their own Thoughts. They will ſit a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon out; but after it is over, and they are gone from it, they are apt to ſay, <hi>Their Lips are their own: Who is Lord over us?</hi> There are thoſe who are yet more Diſobedient and Rebellious; for they will not ſo much as come to the place of Hearing. Others again will Hear and not Obey. And another ſort are <hi>forgetful hearers of the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As when Jeſus Diſcourſed of that <hi>True Bread which cometh down from Heaven, and giveth life unto the World;</hi> The Hearers thereupon ſaid unto him, <hi>Lord evermore give us this Bread,</hi> John 6. 32, 34. So it is evermore the deſire of my Soul; and ſo it is of all Faithful and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People, when we hear ſuch an one is a good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Preacher, or Teacher. <hi>Lord evermore give us the Preaching and Teaching of thy Spirit.</hi> For though the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Teachers ſhould be removed into a corner,</hi> Iſa. 30. 20, Or if the lot of our Habitation is caſt into a Barren Ground, where is a Dead Miniſtry or Dull Teaching; yet the Spirit within us is Life; and by this Spirit we know the Things that are freely given us of God. <hi>For what Man knoweth the things of a Man, ſave the Spirit of a Man which is in him? Even ſo the things of God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no Man but the Spirit of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 10. Even ſo the Elect do know and diſcern more of the Things of God than other People, even by the Spirit which he hath given them. So they do now know and diſcern more of the Appearances and Doings of God unto the World and to his Church, then the mixt Multitude. <hi>Shall the Lord do any thing, and not reveal the ſame unto his Servants the Prophets?</hi> So his Elect Servants do know and receive them for ſuch, that is, for thoſe to whom God doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate himſelf more then to his Ordinary Creatures; when the ſame was not underſtood by the generality of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151750:13"/> the People. There was never yet any true Prophet of the Lord, but who did approve, manifeſt and commend himſelf to the Hearts and Conſciences of ſome of his Servants. And ſo it is, that whereas the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Words of our Text, <hi>Shall know,</hi> that is, in the latter Days, and towards the end of Time, <hi>That there hath been a Prophet among them.</hi> The Elect Servants of God know the very ſame at the Time, and whilſt the Prophet is among them.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Prophets were Ordinary or Extraordinary. By the Ordinary Prophets, I mean the common Prieſts who were to Read and Expound the Law. By the Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Prophets are to be underſtood ſuch, whom God had <hi>Anointed with the Oyl of Gladneſs above their fellows.</hi> To whom he had made known more of himſelf then he had done unto the common Stock and Level of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. The Denomination of the Word Prophet, comes chiefly from <hi>Prophetare;</hi> which ſignifies as much as to <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy voice like a Trumpet, and ſhew my people their Tranſgreſſion, and the houſe of Jacob their ſins,</hi> Iſa. 58. 1. And ſo every common Miniſter or Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the Word, as he is Faithful and True in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that part of the Office, may be called a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet both in the Old and New Teſtament Acceptation; as when we read of the <hi>Schools of the Prophets. Is Saul alſo among the Prophets?</hi> By this Word is denoted that diſtinct Rank of Men, ſuch as are the Prieſts and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy among us at this Day. And ſo we read in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>For ye may all propheſie one by one, that all may learn, and all may be comforted. And the Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets,</hi> 1 Cor. 14, 31. 32. But as one Man now is ſeen to excell another in Strength, Greatneſs, Beauty, Wiſdom, or ſuch like according to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Variety of the Creation and Workmanſhip of God; So the ſame <hi>everlaſting God, the Creator of the ends the Earth,</hi> had alſo amongſt them to whom he Communicated a greater meaſure of his Spirit and of the Knowledge of himſelf and of the things pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto his Kingdom than unto others; as we read in the example of the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151750:13"/>
            <p>Said Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and Saviour, <hi>I muſt go and Preach the Goſpel in other Cities, for thither am I ſent.</hi> And ſo the Prophets and Apoſtles were as <hi>Captives removing to and fro,</hi> Iſa. 49. 21. And travelling from Place to Place for to Preach the Word of God and to make known his Truth. And as <hi>Wiſdom crieth without, ſhe uttereth her voice in the ſtreets: She crieth in the chief place of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, in the openings of the gates; in the City ſhe uttereth her words,</hi> Prov. 1. 20. So their Reſidence or Habitation for the moſt part was in or near the City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the chief City of <hi>Judea,</hi> where the Palaces of their Kings, Rulers and chief of the People were. This I do the more willingly take notice of; becauſe there have been ſome ignorant People in the Neighbourhood of the Place of my Nativity, who did therefore refuſe to hear that part of the Word of the Lord which was committed to my Miniſtration, becauſe they imagine or ſay, I am not long fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and ſettled in the countrey. <hi>O Fooliſh Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Unwiſe!</hi> Should any one therefore refuſe to hear the Antient Prophets, or Chriſt in the Days of his Fleſh, or the Apoſtles, becauſe they did not always tarry in one place? Or refuſe to hear the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prieſts, who were in their time <hi>Worſhippers of the Father,</hi> and accepted with him, becauſe both Prieſts and People did three times in the Year go up to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> The right Practice and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from hence ſhould be for People to hear ſuch a one more gladly, and earneſtly, and to lay hold of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Opportunity, letting none ſlip, becauſe he is not always a Preacher among them. How Ridiculous and Nonſenſical would this ſeem and appear, if People would not go to ſuch Itinerant Judges for Juſtice; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe forſooth they do not come and inhabit in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular place of their abode. And it is a like Errour in Things pertaining to the future and endleſs Life, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to receive <hi>Knowledge at the Prieſts Lips,</hi> Mal. 2. 7. Only becauſe they do according to the eſpecial Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and Appointment of God <hi>Run to and fro,</hi> Dan. 12. 4. For the <hi>increaſe</hi> thereof, and for the Publiſhing and communicating forth of the ſame. Said he, whoſe Example I deſire to follow in this my Generation (for hereby <hi>I ſhall have boldneſs in the Day of Judgment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151750:14"/> as he was, ſo are we in this preſent World) Wiſt ye not that I muſt be about my Fathers buſinefs?</hi> And ſo I ſpeak unto ye my Country Men and Neighbours, Would ye not have me to be about my God and Creatours Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs? What is that? Some of ye may be ready to think and ſay: Why <hi>To declare unto Jacob his Tranſgreſſion, and to Iſrael his Sin.</hi> Micah. 3. 8. <hi>To bring Jacob again un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him,</hi> Iſa. 49. 5. And to endeauour to gain one Point, that is, if I could be ſomewhat inſtrumental by his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Grace, and by the continued goings forth of his eternal Truth <hi>(I will cry unto God moſt High, unto God that performeth all things for me)</hi> to bring over the People of this Nation unto the obedience of one of his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for this would be an inlet and help, and it would make way by degrees, and in ſucceſſion of Time to bring them over unto the Obedience of all the others.</p>
            <p>I have often thought, that if it ſhall appear at the laſt Great Day of the Lord; when <hi>he ſhall write up the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and Rehearſe from the beginning of the World, all things as they were done, that I was a doing the Work of the Lord all along; as it ſeems to be according to his Word and Commandment now: <hi>Thou ſhalt not have thy Brother in thine Heart, Thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy Neighbour and not ſuffer Sin upon him,</hi> Lev. 19. 17. <hi>To teach Tranſgreſſors thy ways, and that ſinners may be converted unto God,</hi> Pſal. 51.: How will they (eſpecially ſome of my neareſt kindred according to the Fleſh) be aſhamed and confounded, who have oppoſed and reproached me; and yet much more will they be aſhamed and confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who have Oppreſſed, Perſecuted and Impriſoned me. Then <hi>the lying lips will be put to ſilence, which ſpeak grievous things proudly and contempuouſly againſt the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> Pſal. 31. 18. And they will wiſh that thoſe Hands had been before that cut off, which have acted cruel and tormenting things againſt me. And they who did not hear, but <hi>they did forbear (for they are a Rebellious Houſe) yet now ſhall know that there hath been a Prophet among them.</hi> That is, one who did faithfully and truly declare and tell them of their Tranſgreſſion and Sin. One who neither had, nor yet did pretend to have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Aſſiſtances or Meaſures of the Spirit, nor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151750:14"/> yet more knowledge than others of his Generation. But as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I thank Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, who hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled me, for that he counted me faithful, putting me into the Miniſtry,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 12. And <hi>He that is faithful in the least, is alſo faithful in much.</hi> So according to that Ability and Knowledge God had given me as his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I have the Teſtimony of mine own Conſcience; That I did endeavour all along to be faithful for the moſt part, even to handle his Word <hi>According to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of my heart, and the skilfulneſs of my hands,</hi> Pſ. 78. 72. And I would <hi>Not hide his Righteouſneſs, nor conceal his Truth,</hi> Pſal. 40. 10. Which aroſe and he made known in my Heart; Though when he <hi>Who gave authority to his Servants, and to every Man his work, and commanded the Porter to watch,</hi> Mark 13. 34. Shall call me to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count about this particular Work he had allotted and ſet out to me; for it is here ſaid, <hi>That he gave to every Man his work.</hi> Herein I ſhall give up ſuch like an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, That as it was managed by me, it was accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſeveral Failures and Imperfections: Yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, this will be ſome joy and leſſening of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Grief; that however I did endeavour to get it done and finiſhed, thinking it better to have it done any way then not at all. <hi>The Lord opened mine ears and I was not Rebellious:</hi> Which will be ſome hope and comfort in that Day. I ought <hi>To have feared no more, nor be diſmay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, neither be lacking.</hi> Jer. 23. 4.</p>
            <p>In the laſt great Day of Judgment, <hi>The Lord will ſhew who are his, and who is holy; and will cauſe him to come near unto him; even him whom he hath choſen, will he cauſe to come near unto him,</hi> Numb. 16. 5. At that Great Day of Deciſion, all Things that are written in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures concerning his Church and People, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his doings towards the Children of Men, will be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled and laid open: Then ſhall be known what Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have been in the ſeveral Generations and Countries. The Lord will recount his <hi>Worthies</hi> and bring them forth by their Names, who were for <hi>Signs and Witneſſes to his People.</hi> Then alſo thoſe Things which are now in the Dark, and which People are in doubt and queſtion whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is any thing of God in it, will be brought to open
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151750:15"/> Light. And then <hi>God, who is judge himſelf, will ſpeak and teſtifie,</hi> Pſal. 50. 6, 7. How He, even He himſelf was concerned therein; and he will make all his Churches, yea, even all his Reaſonable Creatures know that he <hi>was God,</hi> even their God; and conſequently they ſhould have received him for their Lord and Governour.</p>
            <p>Many more things might here be ſpoken as touching this, but for the more full Declaration of them, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to the Hearing of that Day: Both as pertaining how the Caſe ſtands between God and all Mankind in the general; and alſo as to every Individual and Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Soul. For <hi>He who hath Created theſe things, that bringeth out their Hoſt by number, he calleth them all by Names, not one faileth,</hi> will not paſs over nor let ſlip ſo much as one Man or Woman without Examination and Retribution, when the Great Day of his Judgment is come. Whoſe Providence is over the leaſt Things even Sparrows, and the Hairs of our Head, He will <hi>Bring every ſecret thing into Judgment; and we muſt receive for the Deeds done in the Body, whether they be good or bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For we ſhall certainly be called into queſtion for this Day, and ſo of every Days Actions, after that we are come to the Years of Diſcretion, and have the knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dge of Good and Evil. I ſhall give Account of my Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Miniſtry, and ſo the People will of their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and profiting thereby; As alſo, they who refuſe to hear, who <hi>Contemn Gods Word and Commandment,</hi> will be called to an Account: Even thoſe who now <hi>forbear and are Rebellious,</hi> ſhall know, and in the latter Days they ſhall conſider it perfectly, whether they would or not, that there hath been a Prophet among them. I pray God to convince and make it known unto the Inhabita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nts of this Nation, That they may be Wiſe and Diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Time, before it is too late; and that they may know and come to hear the <hi>Things that belong to their peace, before they are hid from their Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much may ſerve for Explanation and Paraphraſe of our Text, and to illuſtrate the Truth thereof: Now let us improve the ſame in ſome few Practical Uſes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:151750:15"/>
            <p>In the Firſt place, Seeing that theſe things are ſo; Hereby may be perceived the exceeding Benefit and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of a knowing and diſcerning Spirit. It is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> That he was <hi>Diſcerning in the Times and Seaſons, that he might know what Iſrael had to do.</hi> This is written for our Admonition, upon whom the Ends of the World are come: To the intent that we alſo ſhould be diſcerning not ſo much in the Times and Seaſons as in the latter and laſt end of things; that we may know what we have to do, in this mean while in the Time of our Probation and Trial; and how we may demean our ſelves in theſe Days of our Fleſh; wherein God doth prove us whether we will keep his Commandments or no. For truly if we did now ſo know and diſcern of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and laſt end of Things, as indeed we ought and may know of the latter and laſt end of Things, and we ſhall be at laſt forced to it, when the <hi>End is come:</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a great deal of Sin and Evil would be avoided and prevented in the mean while; as alſo much Good and Duty might be done, which now through ignorance and want of diſcerning, is left undone. <hi>Eſchew Evil and do Good</hi> is all that God doth require of Man; and the more any one doth eſchew Evil and do Good in the ſeveral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances thereof, it will be ſo much the better for that Man or Woman throughout all Eternity. And accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Knowledge and Faith of People is, ſo they do one or the other. <hi>If ye know theſe Things, happy are ye if ye do them,</hi> Said our Lord to his Diſciples. Nay, if one did fully know ſuch and ſuch Things, and conſider throughly all the Reaſons that perſuade to it, there alſo he would do them; as we find in the Things of Daily Uſe and Experience. For almoſt all Sin doth proceed and ariſe from want of Knowledge. As for inſtance, The Sin of Unbelief doth ariſe from want of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Power of God, what he can do; <hi>As if any thing were too hard for the Lord,</hi> which nothing is. Had <hi>Zacharias</hi> at that very Time known that thoſe Things he was told of <hi>Luke 120. would indeed be performed,</hi> he had not been ſtruck Dumb for his unbelief. And ſo the Sin of Diſtruſt doth ariſe from want of the Knowledge of the Will of God, even what God will do. And ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151750:16"/> when any one falls into a Sin, through ſuch a foregoing Temptation, it is for want of a true and through Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for ſuch ſuppoſe and imagine, that there is more good in the Temptation, then really there is. It is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſaid, <hi>That if we did know before, what would come after, we ſhould never do amiſs.</hi> Which is moſt true, as to the Things pertaining to God, and to our own future State and Condition: As to which, we ſhould never finally miſcarry, if we would receive into our Knowledge, all that God and Chriſt hath told us before concerning it. Our Creatour hath done his part; for he hath made us as Angels of God, capable to know Things before hand; and alſo capable to <hi>Chooſe the good, and refuſe the evil.</hi> But this is the degeneracy of Mankind: This is their fault now, and will be their Condemnation hereafter; That when they were <hi>Made in Honour,</hi> yet themſelves ſhould wilfully become <hi>Of no Underſtanding,</hi> but like the Beaſts that Periſh. That is, to be only for preſent and ſenſible Things, but not to regard the Future and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, which chiefly belong to Man to Mind; becauſe they are his greateſt concern. Saith the Wiſe Man, <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over that the Heart be without Knowledge, it is not good!</hi> Nay, it is ſtark naught; for ſuch being Blinded will inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſlide into the Ditch of Deſtruction. As to thoſe who ſhall finally and eternally Periſh at the laſt Day, The Return will be made, and the Reaſon will be Aſſigned, <hi>My People are deſtroyed for lack of Knowledge,</hi> Hoſ. 4. 6. Which will hold true as to that everlaſting Deſtruction from the Preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his Power. It is not without very good Reaſon, That the Duty of Knowledge is ſo very much inculcated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended in Scripture, which was given to make us wiſe unto Salvation. <hi>Teach me good judgment and knowledge: for I have believed thy Commandments,</hi> Pſal. 119. 66. To the ſame purpoſe is <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. throughout. The neglect of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is threatned and condemned <hi>Iſa. 1. 3. Et. 5. 13. Et. 27. 11. Pſ. 32. 9. Jude. 10. Prov. 27. 22. Jer. 8. 6. Pſ. 14. 4. Eph. 4. 18. Pſ. 82. 5. Pſ. 92. 6. 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 5. In a Word, it is a very great Good, and will be a great Gain to have the knowledge of the Things of God, but chiefly of thoſe things that are to come, as well as of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151750:16"/> Things preſent. So it is a great evil, and will be a great loſs to be found without this Knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> By what hath been aforeſaid from the Words of our Text, may be perceived the much yet greater ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and preciouſneſs of the Grace of FAITH. Saith <hi>Paul, Though I have all Knowledge, and though I have all Faith,</hi> 1 Cor 13. 2. Hereby may be ſeen that Faith is diſtinct from, and doth properly ſucceed and follow after Knowledge: So that we are right enough in making it our ſecond Uſe and Application. The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Faith is future and inviſible Things, according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 1. But the Object of Knowledge is preſent and viſible Things. Now Faith is the Principle and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, the Sum and Subſtance, the Marrow and Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, the very Vitals and Inwards of all Religion. For firſt of all Faith fixes and terminates on the unſeen God, who made all things, both viſible and inviſible; both Things preſent, and Things to come. But then beſides, we are Creatures that are continually paſſing on; we being here in a tranſitory Life, and in a tranſitory State. And we haſt on, and continually make towards thoſe greater and more abiding Things to come. Now as Faith doth diſcover, apprehend, and lay hold of all theſe things, it thereunpon becomes to us all in all. Saith Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Have Faith in God,</hi> Mark 11. 22. And it being elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſaid, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by his Faith.</hi> So that I would chiefly recommend and put my Readers in mind, to have Faith in God, and live by Faith. That as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Whether ye eat or drink, or whatever ye do, do all to the glory of God.</hi> Even ſo, do ye live by Faith, and be full of Faith, and of the Holy Ghoſt; that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye Sleep or Wake, whether ye be buſy or idle, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye be in your Shops, Barns, Houſes or Fields, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye be upon a Journey, or ſitting ſtill; Nay, even whilſt ye are eating your neceſſary Food, or not eating, in whatſoever Poſture or Action ye are in, let your Hearts be always muſing and thinking, and be full with expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, <hi>And looking after thoſe things which are coming on the Earth,</hi> Luke 21. 26. And ſhortly after that we depart hence, will be manifeſted before us with open Face. <hi>For the Diviſions of Reuben, there was great thought and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearching
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151750:17"/> of heart.</hi> So after the inviſible and future things of God, which pertain to us Men, let there be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Thought and ſearching of Heart; <hi>To give all diligence to make our Calling and Election ſure.</hi> Let this be all your Labour and Care: And as ye always Breath, and your Pulſe is continually beating; ſo let your doings and movings be towards and in Subordination and tendency to this great end, how to ſecure and lay hold on the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Things for your Portion. Thus to have <hi>Faith in God,</hi> and to <hi>Live by Faith,</hi> is indeed the way to be <hi>Carried from Faith unto Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Third Practical Uſe and Inference is, To teach every one of us to be of an Obedient, Humble, Lowly and Trembling Spirit. It hath been aforeſaid, that the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Ungodly and Diſobedient, would fain have the Commandments of God be faſhioned according to their imaginations and Luſts; and when they have indeed Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they would ſo make a ſhew, as if they had not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; or as if the Commandments of God were not ſo as they are Recorded in his Book, and delivered by his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters. I have Read among the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayings of <hi>Luther, That nothing diſpleaſeth God more than when we Defend and Cloak our Sins, and will not acknowledge that we have done wrong, as did Saul.</hi> For this is <hi>Adding Sin to Sin,</hi> and a linking one Tranſgreſſion on to another. That is, when ſuch have Sinned or Tranſgreſſed, <hi>In ſpeaking oppreſſion and revolt, conceiving and uttering from the Heart words of falſhood,</hi> Iſa. 59. 13. To vindicate themſelves; and it is a Perſiſting ſtill in their Stubbornneſs, Diſobedience and Rebellion; which inſtead of leſſening doth aggravate and increaſe their Guilt, and it doth provoke God more and more. By that manner of ſpeech, <hi>Conceiving and uttering from the Heart words of falſhood,</hi> Is meant and intended, when People will of ſet purpoſe invent and ſpeak lies and words of Falſhood at the very ſame time when they know it to be ſo, only to cloak and excuſe their foregoing Sins. But all this, both the lying falſe Spirit; as alſo the Perverſe, Diſobedient, Rebellious and Refractory Spirit is far from the Godly; as we may know by the Examples of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151750:17"/>
            <p>By the way, though a parcel of ignorant People or Men pleaſers, who are Corrupted by <hi>filthy lucre,</hi> do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agine or ſay, <hi>That a King or Rich Man, ought not to be Reproved:</hi> Yet we learn and know the contrary from the Word of God, that they both may, and alſo they ought to be Reproved, if they commit Sin or Evil, all one as inferiour People. We may Read in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. That when <hi>Nathan</hi> Reproved <hi>David,</hi> he did not impriſon <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> for it, as <hi>Amaziah</hi> and other Ungodly Kings would ſometimes do unto the Prophets of the Lord; but he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged his Offence. And <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Nathan, I have ſinned againſt the Lord.</hi> And ſo when <hi>Iſaiah</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced that ſad Meſſage to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and his Poſterity, What is the Return and Anſwer which <hi>Hezekiah</hi> made thereupon? <hi>Then ſaid Hezekiah to Iſaiah, Good is the Word of the Lord which thou haſt ſpoken,</hi> Iſa. 39. 8. Both <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> were Servants of the Lord, who were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with a fault; but yet they are for our Example and Inſtruction, how we ſhould behave our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Reproof of the Word, either in the publick Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Miniſtry thereof; or when we are Rebuked privately, as one Man doth his Neighbour. Namely, not to Rankle in Spirit, nor conceive Enmity and Hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the outward Perſon of him that doth it; like <hi>Ahab</hi> to <hi>Micaiah I hate this Man, for he Propheſieth not good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning me; but evil.</hi> Not to kick againſt the Reproof, becauſe it pricks the Conſcience; in which ſenſe, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people harden themſelves now in the mean while, yet hereafter it will be found true, <hi>It is hard to kick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pricks.</hi> Nor yet ſhould any one dare to <hi>Reply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God,</hi> Rom 9, 20. Nor yet as it is in the Marginal Reading there, to Anſwer again; for this is a ſign of a Malapert and Saucy Servant. But as the one is to give, ſo the other ought to receive the Reproof <hi>In the Spirit of meekneſs,</hi> and to acknowledge that he hath <hi>Tranſgreſſed againſt the Lord his God, and that he hath not obeyed his voice,</hi> Jer. 3. 13. But now he is heartily ſorry for it, and unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endly reſolves to mend his fault, and do ſo no more.</p>
            <p>The end and Requiring of the Law, is Obedience: And this is the way when we have not performed that, to make it up and ſupply it, ſo as to render and yield it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151750:18"/> for the time to come. All that God doth require of us, and the only way to pleaſe and be reconciled unto him, is to obey his Word, to have a great fear and dread of the inviſible God in our inward Parts, and a care not to offend him, and to expreſs forth whatever Honour and Reverence we poſſibly can towards him. For though when we are full and in Health, Youth and Strength, we are apt to deſpiſe him, and ſay in our Heart, tuſh God we care not for thee: Yet on the other hand when we are in Hunger, Want, Cold, Affliction or Pain, and more eſpecially when Old Age begins to creep on, when the <hi>Floods come, and the Winds blow and beat upon this houſe</hi> of our Body; when Dangerous and Tormenting Diſeaſes are upon us, and grim Death approaches nigh to Arreſt and Carry our Souls into another place, then we know and are indeed ſenſible, that as God doth Good, ſo he can alſo Puniſh and make the Creature really Miſerable. As when we are Hungry or Cold, or Sick, we would willingly do thoſe things, and uſe thoſe means to be full and ſatisfied, and warm, and well again. So we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>By Nature Children of Wrath,</hi> and liable unto Miſery and Deſtruction, which will at length certainly come upon us, unleſs in God is our help, in God is our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Life and Happineſs; ſo that from hence the Word of Exhortation doth ariſe and run moſt forcible, to actually perſuade us to do thoſe things, and <hi>ſo to walk that we may pleaſe God</hi> that he may do theſe great and good Things on our behalf; Namely, that when Death hath done its worſt and utmoſt upon us, he may raiſe us up again, and give us the <hi>Bleſſing which the Lord hath commanded, even Life for evermore.</hi> That he <hi>Who hath filled the Hungry with good things,</hi> would fill our Hungry Souls with ſatisfaction. <hi>I ſhall be ſatisfied when I awake with thy likeneſs,</hi> Pſal. 17. 15. There is all contained in this Word <hi>Satisfied:</hi> what we can think of or deſire, or would have; for then it will be returned to our unſpeakable rejoycing: Now it is as we would have it. <hi>What Man is he that deſireth Life, and loveth many Days that he may ſee good?</hi> Pſal. 34. 11. So the queſtion may be a little reverſed and altered, What Man
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151750:18"/> is there that doth not deſire Life and many Days that he may ſee Good? For 'tis evident, That if any one doth not deſire many Days, it is becauſe he doth not ſee Good in them; and all this Life, and all this Good, and all this Satisfaction (if I ſhould expreſs it by more words, it is all but the ſame ſtill) is had by Obedience. Saith God to his reaſonable Creatures, <hi>Obey my Voice and Live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the other Branch of this our Third Uſe and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; Namely, That we ſhould be of an Humble, Lowly and Trembling Spirit: It is a part of and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under Obedience to thoſe Commands of our God, <hi>What doth the Lord require of thee, but to walk hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly with thy God,</hi> Micah. 6. 8. <hi>Serve the Lord with fear and rejoyce with Trembling,</hi> Pſal. 2. 11. Verily, verily, we poor mortal Creatures can never be in too low and humble a State; neither can we have too mean an Opinion and Conceit of our ſelves. <hi>For verily every Man at his beſt State; is altogether vanity, Selah,</hi> Pſal. 39. 5. There is the Ratification and Confirmation of it. And as every one of us at our beſt State are altogether Vanity; even ſo we ſhould know and be ſenſible of as much our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, as to lay it deeply to Heart. <hi>Humble your ſelves in the ſight of God, and he ſhall lift you up,</hi> James 4. 10. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your ſelves as nothing and altogether unworthy and unprofitable. Then it was when <hi>David</hi> was <hi>Little in his own ſight.</hi> That God exalted him to be King over all <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and what was Ten Thouſand Times better he gave unto him his holy Spirit, and the <hi>Spirit of God ſpake by him, and his word was in his tongue.</hi> But he giveth more Grace, <hi>Wherefore he ſaith, God reſiſteth the Proud, and giveth grace to the Humble.</hi> Here if they would be ſtill Humble therewith, and uſe it well, he would increaſe even that <hi>More Grace;</hi> for he would give exceeding Gifts unto Men, if they would remain ſtill Low and <hi>Little in their own ſight.</hi> But if once they are <hi>lifted up,</hi> then he hinders, or witholds, or takes away the Qualifications wherein they boaſt, or ſome way defeats and ſpoils them that no Creature ſhould glory in his Preſence. My ſelf am a ſad Example and Warning of this, for <hi>I ſpeak this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my ſhame.</hi> I have perceived from within my ſelf,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151750:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151750:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151750:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151750:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:151750:21"/> drawings of God upon the account of my Spiritual Pride and Affectations of gentility and ſuch like. It is my preſent Teſtimony, and I declare it of mine own miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable Experience; for hereby I ſhall loſe ſo much of that <hi>Full Reward</hi> which I might have had for all Eternity, if I had all along remained <hi>Little in mine own ſight,</hi> and ſuch as a Creature ſhould be. Take heed and beware of Pride, and of the leaſt giving way unto the lifting up of Mind: I mean that which no Man ſeeth, but it is known only between God and thine own Conſcience. As a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid; No Man can be too Low and Humble. So here it is, No Man can keep too far off from Pride, ſo as not to give way unto the Thoughts and Dictates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the leaſt, it being a deadly and dangerous Evil.</p>
            <p>And then for what belongs to this (for fear and humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty commonly go together) that we ſhould always be in a fearful and trembling State, according to what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>And I was with you in Weakneſs, in Fear, and in much Trembling,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 3. It is Obſerved, That in very Cold weather, how little and contracted we are within our ſelves: When we are Cold or Hungry, or in Pain, or in Affliction, then commonly we leaſt ſtand upon, and do not care for, nor value the nicities of Pride. But we are Humble, <hi>viz,</hi> ſuch as frail and miſerable Creatures ſhould be: Even ſo for the very ſame Reaſon, we ſhould <hi>Paſs the time of our ſojourning here in fear.</hi> For the moſt Brittle Glaſs is not more ſubject and liable to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken then we are in all times and places ſubject to Deſtr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uction and Miſery. <hi>For what is our Life? It is even as a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> It is but a puff of Breath in our Noſtrils; And what is more fluid and uncertain then that? Suppoſe a Man were to tread on a Rope an Hundred Yards high, from which if he ſhould fall, he would certainly break his Neck: or ſuppoſe we were to paſs over a wide River or deep Pit on a Bridge, no broader than juſt the Soles of our Feet: and we had nothing at all to hold by, How care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and fearfully ſhould we walk thereon? So is our Caſe and Condition in the Body, and in this Life. For though the Eye of Sence ſeeth it not, yet the Eye of Faith, and the Eyes of our Underſtanding being enlightened
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151750:21"/> do diſcern and know, That we are as yet (it is but for a very little while) kept from the dreadful Things of the inviſible World, only by this thin vail of Fleſh which we carry about us. We are but for a very ſhort reſpite preſerved from drowning by this tottering and ruinous Ark of the Body, which will not preſerve us always. Now if a poor Creature was to ſwim for his Life, he would not be without fear in the midſt of his Swim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, if he hath any ſenſe or apprehenſion of his Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; And if he hath no ſenſe nor apprehenſion of his Danger, then he will be certainly Drowned and Periſh. Juſt ſo is the Condition of all People in this World. <hi>We are by Nature the Children of Wrath, as well as others.</hi> And as ſuch, <hi>Death and Hell followed with him,</hi> Rev. 6. 8. Like a cruel and devouring Dog, doth run after and purſue us. So that the ſame Word which the Angel ſpake unto <hi>Lot,</hi> doth belong to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ery one of us, <hi>Ariſe and eſcape for thy Life.</hi> And truly, unleſs we do ariſe and eſcape for our Life, and unleſs we are warned (as the Preaching and Miniſtry of the Word gives the warning, and unleſs we take the warning, which the Obedience to the ſame word doth. As it is written, <hi>By Faith Noah being warned of God, of things not ſeen as yet, prepared an Ark to the Saving of his Houſe,</hi> Heb. 11. 7. But if it were not for this, we ſhould certainly fall into the Damnation of Hell. And thoſe People, who like Brutes Beaſts go blindfold through the vale of this Life, without any ſence, apprehenſion or fear of the Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no of Hell, they will more certainly fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why any are ſo fearleſs and unconcerned as to this (as too many are) is becauſe they ſee it not. But if Hell Fire was evidently <hi>ſet f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h before their Eyes;</hi> They would be at their wits ends, and think they could never get far enough off from ſo terrible a thing. Even as <hi>Lot</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and eſcape for his Life to avoid the Flames of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah;</hi> So where they ſee it by Faith, will reaſonable people ariſe and eſcape for their Life, to avoid the Fire and Damnation of Hell; all one as we now ſee they do whatever they can to run from an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of Water, of from the Sword of a devouring Enemy. In this laſt Inſtance, when people fly from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151750:22"/> 
               <hi>the Sword, from the drawn Sword and from the greiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of War,</hi> Are they then without fear? In no wiſe, unleſs they ſhut their Eyes, or are ſtupid; and then ſuch are ſooneſt knocked on the Head. Even ſo again it is here, The <hi>laſt Enemy</hi> Death dogs us at our heels: And as it is ſaid in the Book of Revelations, <hi>Hell follows with him.</hi> And can then people live without fear? And yet for all they who live moſt without fear of Hell, will ſooneſt fall into it. I have read of <hi>Damocles</hi> ſitting at a Table feeding upon Dainties and good Chear, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly over his Head there did hang a drawn Sword by a ſingle and weak Thread. Such an one as long as he did not ſee it, might be without fear; but if he did look up and behold it, then he can be no longer heartily and really merry, <hi>No more then Belſhazzar could when he ſaw the hand writing upon the Wall.</hi> In like manner, <hi>The Wrath of God</hi> (which in Scripture is called the Sword of the Lord) <hi>is revealed from Heaven againſt all unrighteouſneſs of Men;</hi> and it hangs directly over all the Children of Diſobedience, and all the Sinners and Tranſgreſſours of the Earth, by the ſingle Thread of their uncertain Lives. For this ſame Wrath of God will be really ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted upon and ſenſibly felt by them after that their Breath is gone out of their Noſtrils, and their Souls are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from their Bodies. How then can any <hi>Live in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure upon the Earth, and be wanton, and nouriſh their hearts as in a day of Slaughter?</hi> Unleſs to compleat the Paralel in this alſo; Herein they become <hi>Like th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Beaſts that Periſh,</hi> As to be quite inſenſible and ignorant thereof. Alas! Notwithſtanding the Brute Beaſts are thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible and ignorant in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n while, they muſt at length come to the ſhambles, and then they ſmell Blood, and they would fain not go, but they are puſhed in. Even ſo thoſe who by multitudes are going on in the way to Death and Hell, when they come near to the firſt, then they begin to know and are ſenſible of the other alſo; but then it is too late, <hi>And the door was ſhut,</hi> Mat. 25. 16. Time paſt cannot be recalled in a Thought; neither will a Deſire at the laſt gaſp be accepted for a godly and well ſpent Life.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:151750:22"/>
            <p>They who in the midſt of Life and Health, go on ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely without the fear of God, and of his Threatnings, and in unmindfulneſs of their Latter End: Even theſe will not be without fear when the Time is come that they muſt Die: But the Soul will indeed Shiver and Tremble, as She is taking her flight forth into the inviſible World. Or if ſhe ſhould be hardened and rendred inſenſible through a foregoing <hi>Deadneſs in Treſpaſſes and Sins;</hi> or through Bodily Pain and Sickneſs, which take up and employ all her Faculties at that time; yet after ſhe is actually diſſolved from this Tabernacle of Clay, then if ſhe is loaden with Sin and Guilt, will ſucceed <hi>A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fearful looking for of Judgment, and fiery Indignation which ſhall devour the Adverſaries,</hi> Heb. 10. 27. For in the World to come there is no hardening againſt God, or the ſence of his Judgments. Therein the <hi>Devils believe and tremble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All people muſt and will fear one time or another. But as the Wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>Happy is he that feareth always;</hi> who fears moſt in this World that he may fear leaſt in the World to come. For from this kind of fear, that is, a fear of God, and a fear to Sin againſt him, doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed a good Conſcience; thence is no fear, that is ſlaviſh or hath torment. Then comes <hi>Perfect love which caſteth out fear.</hi> But as it is written, <hi>When the Sun was going down, a deep ſleep fell upon Abram, and loan horrour of great dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs fell upon him.</hi> So now the Sun of our Life is going down; let it be both our Deſire and Prayer, and alſo Endeavour, that a Filial and Reverential fear, a great Aw and Dread of the inviſible Lord God may fall, and always remain upon our Souls and Spirits. That for theſe very few (now they are fewer then ever they were yet) remaining Days of our Pilgrimage we may <hi>Walk in the fear of the Lord, and in the Comfort of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> againſt the time comes when we are to fall ſeverally <hi>Aſleep in the Lord Jeſus;</hi> and from thence ever to awake after his likeneſs.</p>
            <p>It hath been fulfilled already as to the Inhabitants of this Nation and Generation. The ſame is now ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling whilſt I am Publiſhing theſe things; and it will be yet fulfilled as to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uture kind of behaviour towards
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151750:23"/> my Miniſtry, (For all <hi>will not believe, though a Man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it to them.)</hi> whilſt I go in and out amongſt them. But eſpecially it will be more evidently, clearly and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly fulfilled after that we are all departed off from this Earth, <hi>(Behold I have told you before) And they, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will hear, or whether they will forbear</hi> (Why do not ſome hear, and others forbear) <hi>For they are a Rebellious Houſe.</hi> Notwithſtanding now, they call themſelves Chriſtians; but as <hi>All are not Iſrael, who are of Iſrael,</hi> Rom. 9. 6. So all are not Chriſtians at this Day, who <hi>hold faſt the Name thereof;</hi> Yet <hi>They ſhall know that there hath been a Preacher among them,</hi> who hath Preached the Words of God and of eternal Life.</p>
            <closer>Conſider what hath been ſaid, and the Lord give you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in all things.</closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>So Witneſſeth <hi>RICHARD STAFFORD</hi> a Scribe inſtructed in the Law of GOD, and in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of <hi>JESUS CHRIST.</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> was in the City of <hi>Jeruſalem brought up at the Feet of Gamaliel;</hi> So I was for the ſpace of Six Years Educated at <hi>Magdalen</hi> Hall in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed in the Year, 1700. And are to be Sold unto ſuch who <hi>Will receive the Love of the Truth that they might be ſaved,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 10. And who <hi>will Conſecrate their gain unto the Lord, and their ſubſtance to the Lord of the whole Earth,</hi> Micah. 4. 13. and towards the outward labour and charge of <hi>Making known his Truth.</hi> 38. 19.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
